<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<catalog>
 <cd>
    <title>Chapter 30 Escherichia, Section II: Foodborne diseases due to bacteria. Handbook of Foodborne Diseases. Editado por Dongyou Liu. CRC Press-Taylor and Francis Group.  </title>
    <info>Dongyou Liu. CRC Press-Taylor and Francis Group. Año 2018</info>

    <tipo>Capítulos de Libros</tipo>
    <lugar>Autores: Marta Rivas, Elizabeth S. Miliwebsky, Beatriz D'Astek, Luis A. Pianciola </lugar>
    <anio>2018</anio>
    <abstract>Clearly linked to consumption of foods, beverages, and drinking water that contain pathogenic microbes, toxins, or other toxic agents, foodborne diseases have undergone a remarkable change of fortune in recent decades, from once rare and insignificant malaises to headline-grabbing and deadly outbreaks. 
Unquestionably, several factors have combined to make this happen. 
These include a prevailing demand for the convenience of ready-to-eat or heat-and-eat manufactured food products that allow ready entry and survival of some robust, temperature-insensitive microorganisms; a drastic reduction in the costs of air, sea, and road transportation that has taken some pathogenic microorganisms to where they were absent previously; an expanding world population that has stretched the boundary of human activity; and an ageing population whose weakened immune functions provide a fertile ground for opportunistic pathogens to invade and thrive.


Given the diversity of causative agents (ranging from viruses, bacteria, yeasts, filamentous fungi, protozoa, helminthes, toxins, to toxic agents), and the ingenuity of pathogenic microbes to evolve through genetic reassortment, horizontal gene transfer, and/or random genetic mutation, it has become an enormous challenge to understand how foodborne agents are able to evade host immune defenses and induce diseases, and also to develop and apply innovative approaches for improved diagnosis, treatment, and prevention of foodborne diseases.

Handbook of Foodborne Diseases summarizes the latest findings on more than 100 foodborne diseases and their causative agents. With contributions from international experts on foodborne pathogens, toxins, and toxic agents research, this volume provides state-of-the-art overviews on foodborne diseases in relation to their etiology, biology, epidemiology, clinical presentation, pathogenesis, diagnosis, treatment, and prevention. Apart from offering a comprehensive textbook for undergraduate and postgraduate students in food, medical, and veterinary microbiology, this volume constitutes a valuable reference on foodborne diseases for medical professionals and health authorities, and forms an informative educational resource for the general public.
    
    </abstract>


  </cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Escherichia coli diarreigénico. Actualizacion en epidemiología, patogénesis, clínica, tratamiento, prevención y diagnóstico en el paciente con diarrea. </title>
    <info>Editorial Académica Española. Año 2018</info>

    <tipo>Capítulos de Libros</tipo>
    <lugar>Autores: Marta Rivas (Ed.), Elizabeth S. Miliwebsky, Luis A. Pianciola </lugar>
    <anio>2018</anio>
    <abstract>Escherichia coli diarreigénico. Actualizacion en epidemiología, patogénesis, clínica, tratamiento, prevención y diagnóstico en el paciente con diarrea.
    
    A nivel mundial, la enfermedad diarreica constituye un problema grave para la salud pública de infantes y niños, con altas tasas de morbilidad y mortalidad,
    especialmente en paises en desarrollo. La diarrea de origen infeccioso puede ser de etiología bacteriana, viral o parasitaria, siendo frecuentes las asociaciones
    de dos o más agentes. La mayoría de las cepasde Escherichia coli no son patógenas; sin embargo, algunas de ellas pueden ser patógenos oportunistas que causan 
    infecciones intestinales y extraintestinales. Con el nombre de E. coli diarreigénico (DEC)se denomina a un grupo heterogéneo de cepas que poseen distintos factores 
    de virulencia y distinta interacción con la mucosa intestinal del hospedador, causas diferentes sindromes diarreicos y tienen distinta epidemiología. 
    El objetivo propuesto en la presente edición ha sido poner a diposición de médicos y microbiologos clínicos una revisión y actualizacion de los factores de virulencia,
    mecanismos de patogenicidad, epidemiología, tratamiento y diagnóstico microbiológico de DEC.Tambien se incluye un capítulo sobre el manejo clínico del paciente con 
    diarrea aguda.
    
    </abstract>


  </cd>
  <cd>
    <title>Estudio de brotes de gastroenteritis por Norovirus en la provincia de Neuquén en el periodo 2014-2016. </title>
    <info>Zitta M, Hadad F, Navello M, Mazzeo M, Müller M, Zurschmitten A, Pianciola L. </info>
 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>IV International Clinical Virology Symposium and Advances in Vaccines. Buenos Aires, Argentina, 24 a 26 de octubre de 2016.</lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  
    
  </cd>
  <cd>
  <title>Validación multicéntrica de dos PCR multiples para el diagnóstico y confirmación de diferentes categorías de Escherichia coli diarreigénicos</title>
    <info>Miliwebsky E, D’Astek B, Carbonari C, Manfredi E, Baschkier A, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Zotta M, Oderiz S, Zamboni M, Irazu L, Chinen I, Rodríguez M, Rivas M. 
    </info>
 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>XXIII Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología-XIV Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Rosario, Argentina, 26 a 30 de Septiembre de 2016.</lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
   
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>
 <title>Prevalencia de infecciones por Chlamydia trachomatis y Trichomonas vaginalis en mujeres asintomáticas de la ciudad de Chos Malal, Neuquén, Argentina</title>
    <info>Tesoniero A, Codorniú C, Encina F, Mazzeo M, Mora J, Navello M, Zitta M, Pianciola L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XXIII Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología-XIV Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Rosario, Argentina, 26 a 30 de Septiembre de 2016.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
     <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>
 <title>Prevalencia y caracterización molecular de cepas de Escherichia coli O157 aisladas de ganado vacuno en Chos Malal, Neuquén, Argentina. </title>
    <info>Mazzeo M, D’Astek B, Zitta M, Zolezzi G, Navello M, Deza N, Müller M, Pianciola L, Rivas M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>XXIII Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología-XIV Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Rosario, Argentina, 26 a 30 de Septiembre de 2016.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>
<title>Perfil lipídico del liquido hidatídico obtenido de quistes de ovinos y caprinos infectados con diferentes genotipos de Echinococcus granulosus sensu lato. </title>
    <info>Pierangeli N, Debiaggi M, Silva R, Lazzarini L, Sánchez Thevenet P, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Álvarez H, Martínez J, Veuthey V, Soriano S, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>XXIII Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología-XIV Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Rosario, Argentina, 26 a 30 de Septiembre de 2016.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>

<title>Ciclos sinantrópicos de Echinococcus granulosus sensu lato en Neuquén: hospedadores y genotipos involucrados. </title>
    <info>Debiaggi M, Lazzarini L, Roccia I, Pierangeli N, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Martínez J, Veuthy B, Bergagna H, Soriano S, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>XXX Jornadas Nacionales de Hidatidosis. Santa Fe, 26 y 27 de noviembre de 2015.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>
  <title>Aplicación de las técnicas de SDS-PAGE y WESTERN BLOT en la caracterización antigénica de Echinococcus granulosus de origen porcino para su uso en inmunodiagnóstico</title>
    <info>Debiaggi M, Lazzarini L, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Veuthy B, Martínez J, Kossman A, Bergagna H, Soriano S, Pierangeli N. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>II Jornadas Patagónicas de Bioquímica organizadas por la Federación Bioquímica Patagónica. General Roca, Río Negro, 26 a 28 de noviembre de 2015. Trabajo acreedor del Primer Premio al mejor trabajo de las Jornadas. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>




  <cd>

  <title>Diferencias en el perfil proteico de líquido hidatídico obtenido de diferentes operadores y genotipos de Echinococcus granulosus. </title>
    <info>Debiaggi M, Pierangeli N, Lazzarini L, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Martínez J, Veuthy B, Bergagna H, Soriano S, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>VII Congreso Argentino de Parasitología organizado por la Asociación Parasitológica Argentina. San Carlos de Bariloche, 1° a 5 de noviembre de 2015. Seleccionado para presentación oral. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Estudio comparativo de la medida de ganchos rostelares entre el estado larvario y estrobilar de Echinococcus canadensis genotipo G6.  </title>
    <info>Debiaggi M, Soriano S, Lazzarini L, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Martínez J, Veuthy B, Bergagna H, Pierangeli N, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>VII Congreso Argentino de Parasitología organizado por la Asociación Parasitológica Argentina. San Carlos de Bariloche, 1° a 5 de noviembre de 2015. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>



  <cd>
   <title>Hypervirulent Escherichia coli O157 in surface waters near feedlots. </title>
    <info>Tanaro JD, Pianciola L, D’Astek B, Piaggio M, Gasparovic A, Rivas M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>9th. Triennal International Symposium on Shiga Toxin Producing Escherichia coli Infections-VTEC2015-, Septiembre 13 a 15. Boston-Massachusets, EEUU. Seleccionado para presentación oral
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>



  <cd>
   <title>Implementation of Whole Genome Sequencing based STEC Surveillance in Argentina.</title>
    <info> Chinen I, Carbonari C, Campos J, Pianciola L, Masana M, Epszteyn S, Pérez E, Timme R, Luo Y, Wang C, Evans P, Rivas M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>Triennal International Symposium on Shiga Toxin Producing Escherichia coli Infections-VTEC2015-, Septiembre 13 a 15. Boston-Massachusets, EEUU. Seleccionado para presentación oral.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>
<title>Whole-Genome Sequencing applied to the molecular epidemiology of Shiga Toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 in Argentina.</title>
    <info>  Carbonari C, Fitipaldi N, Athey T, Teatero S, Pianciola L, Melano R, Rivas M, Chinen I. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>Triennal International Symposium on Shiga Toxin Producing Escherichia coli Infections-VTEC2015-, Septiembre 13 a 15. Boston-Massachusets, EEUU. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>

    <abstract>Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli strains are worldwide associated with sporadic human infections and outbreaks. In this work, we report the availability of high-quality draft whole-genome sequences for 19 O157:H7 strains isolated in Argentina.</abstract></cd>
  <cd>
<title>Comparison of genomic features of Escherichia coli O157:H7 strains of bovine and human origin isolated in Argentina. </title>
    <info>  Carbonari C, Fitipaldi N, Athey T, Teatero S, Pianciola L, Melano R, Rivas M, Chinen I. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>Triennal International Symposium on Shiga Toxin Producing Escherichia coli Infections-VTEC2015-, Septiembre 13 a 15. Boston-Massachusets, EEUU. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2015</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>
<title>Informe especial “Síndrome Urémico Hemolítico en Argentina, 2010-2013.  </title>
    <info>Julián Antman, Laura Geffner, Luis Pianciola, Marta Rivas. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>Boletín Integrado de Vigilancia, Ministerio de Salud de la Nación. 222 (SE30), 92-112. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>
<title>Epidemiología molecular de la Echinococcosis en la provincia de Neuquén. </title>
    <info>3° Congreso Argentino de Facultades y Escuelas de Medicina Públicas: “La investigación médica que el país necesita. Responsabilidad social de las Carreras de Medicina. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>Universidad Nacional del Litoral. Santa Fe. 18, 19 y 20 de septiembre de 2014. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>

<title>Metapneumovirus Humano en infecciones respiratorias agudas de la provincia de Neuquén, periodo 2010-2013. </title>
    <info>Zitta, M; Navello, M; Mueller, M; Mazzeo, M; Pianciola, L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XV Jornadas Argentinas de Microbiología. Córdoba. 14 a 16 de agosto de 2014.  
  </lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>


<title>Epidemiología molecular de la echinococcosis quística en porcinos de la Provincia de Neuquén.
</title>
    <info> Lazzarini L, Soriano S, Pierangeli N, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Debiaggi F, Kossman A, Vittori L, Bergagna H, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>III Congreso Panamericano de Zoonosis-VIII Congreso Argentino de Zoonosis. La Plata (Buenos Aires). 4 a 6 de Junio de 2014.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>

<title>Caracterización de antígenos de Echinococcus granulosus de origen porcino utilizando SDS-PAGE y Western Blot. 
</title>
    <info> Debiaggi F, Pierangeli N,  Soriano S, Lazzarini L, Pianciola L, Vittori L,  Kossman A, Mazzeo M, Bergagna H, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>III Congreso Panamericano de Zoonosis-VIII Congreso Argentino de Zoonosis. La Plata (Buenos Aires). 4 a 6 de Junio de 2014.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>

<title>Caracterización de la Epidemiología Molecular de la Hidatidosis Bovina en Neuquén, Argentina. 
</title>
    <info> Pierangeli, NB; Lazzarini, LE; Soriano, SV; Pianciola, LA; Mazzeo, M; Bergagna, H; Debiaggi, MF; Vittori, L; Basualdo, JA. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XXVIII Jornadas Nacionales de Hidatidosis, Bariloche, Río Negro. 10 y 11 de Octubre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>

<title>Caracterización de antígenos de Echinococcus granulosus de origen caprino utilizando SDS-PAGE y western blot. 
</title>
    <info>Pierangeli Nora B, Debiaggi María F, Kossman Alejandra V, Pianciola Luis A, Soriano Silvia V, Lazzarini Lorena E, Mazzeo Melina L, Bergagna Héctor F, Vittori Lourdes E, Basualdo Juan A.
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar> XXVIII Jornadas Nacionales de Hidatidosis, 10-11 de octubre de 2013, San Carlos de Bariloche.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>

<title>Caracterización del perfil antigénico del líquido hidatídico de Echinococcus granulosus genotipos G6 y G7 para su aplicación al inmunodiagnóstico de hidatidosis humana. 
</title>
    <info>N Pierangeli, M Debiaggi, L Pianciola, S Soriano, L Lazzarini, M Mazzeo, H Bergagna, A Kossman, L Vittori, J Basualdo. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>


<title>Vigilancia de la resistencia a macrólidos en aislamientos de Bordetella pertussis de Argentina. 
</title>
    <info>Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Flores D, Navello M, Fiori  S,  Zitta E, Bottero D,  Müller C,  Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>


    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>
<title>Brote alimentario por Salmonella Typhimurium en Neuquén.
</title>
    <info> Moroni M, Sauer H, González G, G Gottardi, López C, Pianciola L, Mazzeo F, Mazzeo M, Olivieri E, Larraburu G, Campos J, Alcain A, Caffer MI, Galas M, Pichel M, Viñas MR. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>
<title>Encefalitis letal tóxica asociada a gastroenteritis por Shigella flexneri. 
</title>
    <info>Mazzeo, M; González, G; Muller, M; Lopez, C; Zitta, M; Kaltenbach German; Navello, M; Pianciola, L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>
<title>Hiperplasia epitelial multifocal: presentación y descripción de casos en la provincia de Neuquén. 
</title>
    <info>Zitta, M; Pianciola, L; Suarez, L; Müller, M; Navello, M; Marín, V; Serrano, C; Mazzeo, M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>

<title>Vesículas de membrana externa derivadas de Bordetella parapertussis como una vacuna acelular contra Bordetella parapertussis y la infección por Bordetella pertussis. 

</title>
    <info>Bottero D, Gaillard ME, Errea A, Moreno G, Zurita, E, Pianciola L , Rumbo M y Hozbor D.  
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XIII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología 2013. Buenos Aires, 23 al 26 de septiembre de 2013. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>

<title>Red de diarreas bacterianas y patógenos de transmisión alimentaria: Experiencia en la vigilancia de Escherichia coli productor de toxina Shiga en Neuquén. 

</title>
    <info>L Pianciola, I Chinen, G Gottardi, M Mazzeo, E Miliwebsky, G González, C Carbonari, M Navello, F Mazzeo, C López, M Rivas. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XI Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología e Higiene de los Alimentos. Buenos Aires, Noviembre de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

   <cd>

<title>Vigilancia de Yersinia spp en alimentos cárneos: experiencia en Neuquén. 

</title>
    <info>Gottardi G, Mazzeo M, Mazzeo F, Navello M, Sauer H, Zitta M, Müller M, Pianciola L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XI Congreso Latinoamericano de Microbiología e Higiene de los Alimentos. Buenos Aires, Noviembre de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
     <cd>

<title>Caracterización de antígenos de Echinococcus granulosus de origen caprino utilizando SDS-PAGE y WESTERN BLOT. 

</title>
    <info>Pierangeli N, Debiaggi MF, Kosmann A, Pianciola L, Soriano S, Lazzarini L, Mazzeo M, Bergagna H, Vittori L, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>XXVII Jornadas Argentinas de Hidatidosis - XXXV Jornadas Internacionales de Hidatidología. Puerto Madryn, Chubut. 8 y 9 de Noviembre de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
       <cd>

<title>Epidemiología molecular de la Echinococcosis Quística en bovinos de Neuquén, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>Lazzarini L, Pierangeli N, Soriano S, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Bergagna H, Debiaggi MF, Vittori L, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>Trabajo seleccionado para presentación oral. VI Congreso Argentino de Parasitología, II Jornadas Bioquímicas del Sudoeste Bonaerense. Bahía Blanca, 17 a 19 de octubre de 2012. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
      <cd>

<title>Parámetros Bioquímicos del Líquido Hidatídico en relación con las características del quiste y con el genotipo de Echinococcus. 

</title>
    <info>Pierangeli N, Debiaggi MF, Pianciola L, Soriano SV, Kosmann A, Lazzarini L, Mazzeo M, Vittori L, Basualdo JA. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>I Jornadas Patagónicas de Bioquímica – VII Jornadas Día del Bioquímico. Comodoro Rivadavia, 4 a 6 de octubre de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
    <cd>

<title>Características clínico epidemiológicas de coqueluche y su relación con la situación socioeconómica de la población. 

</title>
    <info>Pianciola L, Bottero D, Mazzeo M, Flores D, Navello M, Zitta E, Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>VII Congreso de la Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología, Micología y Parasitología Clínicas, SADEBAC 2012. Buenos Aires, 26 a 29 de Junio de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
     <cd>

<title>Rol de Mycoplasma pneumoniae y Chlamydophila pneumoniae en neumonías adquiridas en la comunidad que requieren internación

</title>
    <info> Mazzeo M, Navello M, Zitta E, Pianciola L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>VII Congreso de la Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología, Micología y Parasitología Clínicas, SADEBAC 2012. Buenos Aires, 26 a 29 de Junio de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>

<title>Evaluación de la participación de canes en la contaminación del medio ambiente por Campylobacter spp. 

</title>
    <info>Castaño V, Navello M, Mazzeo M, Zitta E, Pianciola L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
<lugar>VII Congreso de la Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología, Micología y Parasitología Clínicas, SADEBAC 2012. Buenos Aires, 26 a 29 de Junio de 2012. Trabajo seleccionado para PRESENTACIÓN ORAL.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
    <cd>

<title>Perfil bioquímico del líquido hidatídico y su relación con el hospedador, localización, genotipo, fertilidad y viabilidad.

</title>
    <info> Pierangeli N, Soriano S, Kossman A, Sanchez Thevenet P, Lazzarini L, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Debiaggi M, Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>VII Congreso de la Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología, Micología y Parasitología Clínicas, SADEBAC 2012. Buenos Aires, 26 a 29 de Junio de 2012. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>

  </cd>

<cd>

<title>Resurgencia de coqueluche en Argentina: caracterización de la sintomatología en pacientes menores de 1 año de edad. 

</title>
    <info>Flores D, Fiori S, Bottero D, Lara C, Pianciola L, Basile L, Ormazabal M, Sorhouet C, Rugeri D, Galas M, Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>

      <lugar>VII Congreso de la Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología, Micología y Parasitología Clínicas, SADEBAC 2012. Buenos Aires, 26 a 29 de Junio de 2012. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

<cd>

<title>Hypervirulent Escherichia coli O157:H7 strains that cause hemolytic uremic syndrome in Neuquén, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>Pianciola, L., Chinen, I., Mazzeo, M., Zolezzi, G., González, G., D’Astek, B., Deza, N., Navello, M., Rivas, M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>8th International Symposium on Shiga Toxin (verocytotoxins) producing Escherichia coli infections. VTEC 2012. Amsterdam, Holanda. 6 a 9 de Mayo de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>


<cd>

<title>Epidemiología descriptiva de casos de coqueluche causados por Bordetella parapertussis.

</title>
    <info> Pianciola L., Bottero D., Mazzeo M., Flores D., Navello M., Zitta E., Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>III Congreso Internacional de Infectología Pediátrica y Vacunas. Buenos Aires, 18 y 19 de Abril de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

<cd>

<title>Coqueluche en Argentina: descripción de la situación epidemiológica durante el período 2008-2011. 

</title>
    <info> Flores D., Lara C., Bottero D., Giovacchini C., Fiori, S., Sorhouet C., Pianciola L., Ruggeri, D., Antman J., Zurita, E., Mazzeo M, Galas,M, Sagradini, S., Vizzotti C., Echenique H. y Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>III Congreso Internacional de Infectología Pediátrica y Vacunas. Buenos Aires, 18 y 19 de Abril de 2012.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>  <abstract></abstract>

  </cd>

<cd>

<title>Identificación de reservorios de Echinococcus  canadensis en Neuquén, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info> Soriano, S. V.,  Pianciola, L. A., Pierangeli, N. B., Lazzarini, L. E., Mazzeo, M., Kossman, A. V., Núñez, R. A., Vittori, L. E., Debiaggi, F., Basualdo, J. A. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>XXX Jornadas Internacionales de Hidatidología. Jujuy, 10 a 12 de noviembre de 2011.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2011</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
<cd>

<title>Medida de ganchos rostelares para diferenciación de especies y genotipos de Echinococcus granulosus. 

</title>
    <info> Soriano, S. V., Pierangeli, N., Lazzarini, L., Pianciola, L., Mazzeo, M., Kossman, A., Basualdo, J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
     <lugar>I Congreso Internacional de Zoonosis y Enfermedades Emergentes y VII Congreso Argentino de Zoonosis. Bs As, 8 a 10 de Junio de 2011.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2011</anio>
  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
<cd>

<title>Human metapneumovirus (hMPV) and influenza like infections (ILI) in Neuquén, Argentina, during 2010. 

</title>
    <info> Pianciola L., Navello M., Fernandez C., Bulgheroni F., Gonzalez G., Mazzeo M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
       <lugar>III International Clinical Virology Symposium and advances in vaccines. 8 a 10 de Noviembre 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  <cd>

<title>Cepas hipervirulentas de Escherichia coli O157:H7: detección en Neuquén de un linaje asociado a patologías severas. 

</title>
    <info> Pianciola L., Navello M., Fernandez C., González G., Di Russo V., Amarilla N., Mazzeo M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
      <abstract></abstract>

  </cd>

  <cd>

<title>Diarreas Bacterianas: evaluación de los métodos tradicionales de diagnóstico, utilizando herramientas moleculares. 

</title>
    <info> Mazzeo M., Navello M., Gonzalez G., Bulgheroni F., Sauer H., Pianciola L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>

<title>Aplicación de la técnica de Multilocus Variable Number of Tandem Repeat Analysis a la vigilancia epidemiológica de Escherichia coli O157:H7 en Argentina. 

</title>
    <info> Chinen I., Hyytia-Trees E., Sabor A., Cisterna D., Miliwebsky E., Deza N., Suárez ME., González G., Esquivel P., Pianciola L., Rivas M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
   <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

 <cd>

<title>Caracterización molecular de aislamientos de Echinococcus (Sensu lato) obtenidos de hospedadores intermediarios en la Provincia de Neuquén, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info> Soriano SV, Pierangeli NB, Pianciola LA, Mazzeo M, Lazzarini LE, Saiz MS, Kossman AV, Bergagna HFJ, Chartier K, Basualdo JA. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

 <cd>

<title>Aislamiento de Yersinia enterocolitica en pacientes con diarrea en un hospital de Neuquén.

</title>
    <info> Gonzáez G, Sauer H, Amarilla A, Mazzeo M, Navello M, Pianciola L, Bulgheroni MF.  
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
   <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

 <cd>

<title>Epidemiología de pertussis en Argentina durante el período 2006-2010: tendencias por grupo de edad y estado de vacunación. 

</title>
    <info>Lara C, Flores D, Zurita E, Sorhouet C, Fioriti A, Fiori S, Bottero D, Barbero P, Bettiol M, Gatti B, Graieb A, Weltman G, González Ayala S, Galas M, Pianciola L, Hozbor D. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

 <cd>

<title>Detección de Escherichia coli O157:H7 perteneciente al hipervirulento clado 8 en bovinos de Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>Larzabal M, Rabinovitz BC, Baldone V, Moreira AR, Elizondo AM, Viste DA, Mazzeo M, Cataldi A, Pianciola L, Mercado EC. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>XII Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. 17 a 20 de Octubre de 2010. Buenos Aires.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
     <abstract></abstract>

  </cd>
<cd>

<title>Prospective laboratory-based surveillance for community clusters of shigellosis in Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>Galas M, Viñas M, Pichel M, Stelling J, Yih K, Tuduri E, Kulldorff M, Van der Ploeg C, Pianciola L, Gottardi G, Sauer H, Di Russo V, Zurschmitten A, Hadad M F, Nuñez M, Brasili S, Schinchirimini M, 1Goya F, Carranza C, Riera M, De Bunder S, Blazquez N, Nobile M, Gallardo D, Santagni A, Vazquez G, Almada G, Wurst S, Pereyra A, Silveyra I, Rechimont C, Ottavianoni L, and Terragno R.  
    </info> 
  <lugar>50th.Conference on Antimicrobial agents and Chemotherapy (ICAAC 2010). Septiembre 12 a 15, 2010. Boston. USA.</lugar>
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <anio>2010</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>

<cd>

<title>Epidemiology of pertussis in Argentina during the 2006-2010 period: trends by age group and status of vaccination. Possible source of infection. 

</title>
    <info>Flores D., Lara C., Zurita E., Sorhouet C., Fioriti A., Fiori S., Bottero D., Barbero P., Bettiol M., Gatti B., Pianciola L., Mazzeo M., Zamboni M., Anchart E., Graieb A., Gonzalez Ayala S., Galas M., Hozbor D.  
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
  <lugar>Nineth Internacional Bordetella Symposium. September 30-October 3, 2010. Baltimore, MD. USA.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

<cd>

<title>Identification of possible reservoirs of Echinococcus granulosus G6 strain in Neuquén, Patagonia Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>Soriano S., Pierangeli N., Pianciola L., Mazzeo M., Lazzarini L., Saiz M., Bergagna H., Chartier K., Basualdo J. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
    <lugar>XXIII International Congress of Hidatidology. Colonia del Sacramento, Uruguay. 9 a 11 de Diciembre de 2009.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>

    <abstract></abstract></cd>
<cd>

<title>Differential epidemiological characteristics of the pertussis outbreak registered in a southern province of Argentina.

</title>
    <info> L. Pianciola, G. Weltman, A. Graieb, F Bulgheroni, M. Fingermann, V. Di Russo, A. Fioriti, E., C. Lara, Zurita, D. Archuby, D. Flores, D. Bottero, ME Gaillard, M. Regueira, M. Galas, D. Hozbor. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>6th World Congress of the World Society for Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Buenos Aires, Argentina, 19 a 22 de Noviembre de 2009.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>  <abstract></abstract>

  </cd>

<cd>
<title>Pertussis: nuevas estrategias diagnósticas aportan información desconocida sobre su epidemiologia en Argentina y en Neuquén

</title>
    <info>. Pianciola, L., Mazzeo, M., Bulgheroni, F., Bottero, D., Hozbor, D.
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>IV Jornadas Patagónicas Materno Infantil. 4 y 5 de Septiembre de 2009. Neuquén.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Screening de Escherichia coli productor de toxina Shiga por PCR en pacientes con diarrea en Hospital Horacio Heller, Neuquén, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>G. González, L. Pianciola, V. di Russo, E. Miliwebsky, N. Deza, C. Carbonari, I. Chinen, M. Rivas. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>IV Jornadas Patagónicas Materno Infantil. 4 y 5 de Septiembre de 2009. Neuquén.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Diarreas bacterianas: evaluación de los métodos tradicionales de diagnóstico, utilizando herramientas moleculares.

</title>
    <info> Mazzeo, M., Navello, M., Quidel, N., Paniconi, M.,   González, G., Bulgheroni, F., Pianciola, L. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>IV Jornadas Patagónicas Materno Infantil. 4 y 5 de Septiembre de 2009. Neuquén.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Escherichia coli O157:H7: brotes en San Martín de los Andes, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info> G. Gonzélez, L. Pianciola, V. di Russo, S. Crespo, J. Rojas, I. Chinen, N. Deza, C. Carbonari, B. D’Astek, E. Miliwebsky, M. Rivas. 


    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>IV Jornadas Patagónicas Materno Infantil. 4 y 5 de Septiembre de 2009. Neuquén.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Screening of Shiga Toxin producing Escherichia coli by PCR in patients with diarrhea in Neuquén city, Argentina. 

</title>
    <info>G. González, L. Pianciola, V. di Russo, E. Miliwebsky, N. Deza, C. Carbonari, I. Chinen, M. Rivas. 


    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>7th International Symposium on Shiga Toxin (Verocytotoxin)-Producing Escherichia coli. VTEC 2009. Buenos Aires, 10 a 13 de Mayo de 2009.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Escherichia coli O157:H7 outbreaks, San Martín de los Andes, Neuquén, Argentina.

</title>
    <info> G. González, L. Pianciola, V. di Russo, S. Crespo, J. Rojas, I. Chinen, N. Deza, C. Carbonari, B. D’Astek, E. Miliwebsky, M. Rivas. 


    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>7th International Symposium on Shiga Toxin (Verocytotoxin)-Producing Escherichia coli. VTEC 2009. Buenos Aires, 10 a 13 de Mayo de 2009.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Bordetella parapertussis: detección de un patógeno para el que no existe una estrategia específica de control. 

</title>
    <info>Pianciola, L., Mazzeo, M., Bottero, D., Zurita, E., Archuby, D., Almuzara, M., Vay, C., Hozbor, D. 


    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>XIII Jornadas Argentinas de Microbiología. Rosario. 9 a 11 de Octubre de 2008.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2008</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Características epidemiológicas de casos de pertussis registrados en Centros Nacionales de Referencia durante los años 2006 – 2007. 

</title>
    <info>Flores, D., Zurita E., Lara C., Weltman G., Archuby D., Fioriti A., Graieb A., Roberts R., Fingermann M., Bottero D., Sisti F., Gaillard, M., Fernández, J., Pianciola L., Lescano M. , Dibiase D., Callejo R. , Regueira M., Binsztein N., Rico O., Ríos G. Galas M., Hozbor D.

    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>6º Congreso Argentino de Infectología Pediátrica. Buenos Aires, 16 a 19 de Abril de 2008.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2008</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Sindrome Urémico Hemolítico (SUH) en la Provincia de Neuquén: Resultados de la búsqueda de Escherichia coli productor de toxina Shiga (STEC). 

</title>
    <info>González, G., Pianciola, L., Bulgheroni, M., Sauer, H., López, C., Milliwebsky, E., Deza, N., Baschkier, A., Rivas, M. 

    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>XI Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Córdoba, 10 a 12  de Octubre de 2007.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
    
  <cd>
<title>Situación epidemiológica de coqueluche en la Provincia de Neuquén. 
</title>
    <info>Pianciola, L., González, G., Mazzeo, M., Weltman, G., Regueira, M., Binsztein, N., Lescano, M., Fingermann, M., Graieb, A., Hozbor, D.
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>XI Congreso Argentino de Microbiología. Córdoba, 10 a 12  de Octubre de 2007.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Diagnosis and phylogenetic characterization of HTLV- 1/2 infection in pregnant women from Argentina. 
</title>
    <info>Eirin ME, Berini C, Torres O, Benedicti M, Lugones S, Pianciola L, Nadal M, Pando M, Biglione M. 
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>13th International Conference on Human Retrovirology: HTLV and related retroviruses. Hakone, Japan. My 22-25, 2007.
  </lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Epidemiological characteristics of pertussis in Argentina 2003-2006. 
</title>
    <info>Graieb A, Roberts R, Fingermann M, Bottero D, Sisti F, Gaillard M, Fernández J, Pianciola L, Lescano M, Dibiase D, Regueira M, Binsztein N, Rico O, Rios G and Hozbor D.
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>The Tenth Annual Conference on Vaccine Research. Baltimore, MD, USA. 30 de Abril a 2 de Mayo de 2007. 
  </lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  
  <cd>
<title>Molecular differences between Bordetella pertussis circulating strains and strains used for vaccine production: Implication in the efficiency of pertussis vaccine. 
</title>
    <info>Gaillard M, Sisti F, Graieb A, Fernández J, Bottero D,  Fingermann M, Roberts R, Pianciola L, Rico O, and Hozbor D.  
    </info> 
   <tipo>Presentaciones a Congresos</tipo>
      <lugar>The Tenth Annual Conference on Vaccine Research. Baltimore, MD, USA. 30 de Abril a 2 de Mayo de 2007.  
  </lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  
  <!--proyectos-->

  <cd>
    <title>Close study for integrated surveillance of Salmonella spp. in the poultry chain and clinical isolates with emphasis on antimicrobial resistance in Neuquén province during a year.
    </title>
    <info>Seleccionado para su financiamiento por Advisory Group on Integrated Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance (AGISAR), Organización Mundial de la Salud. Proyecto coordinado a nivel nacional por INEI/ANLIS “Dr. Carlos G. Malbrán” y en la provincia por el Laboratorio Central de Neuquén. Año 2017.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>


  <cd>
    <title>Análisis genómico de cepas de Escherichia coli O157:H7 aisladas de los reservorios bovino y ambiental en Argentina, y su relación con cepas de origen humano.
    </title>
    <info>
      Coordinado por Servicio de Fisiopatogenia, INEI-ANLIS “Dr. Carlos G. Malbrán”. Financiado por los Fondos Concursables ANLIS (FOCANLIS). Año 2014.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>



  <cd>
    <title>Validación de dos PCR múltiples para el diagnóstico y confirmación de las diferentes categorías de Escherichia coli diarreigénicos.
    </title>
    <info>
      Coordinado por Servicio de Fisiopatogenia, INEI-ANLIS “Dr. Carlos G. Malbrán”. Financiado por los Fondos Concursables ANLIS (FOCANLIS). Año 2013.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>



  <cd>
    <title>Epidemiología molecular de la Echinococcosis en la Provincia de Neuquén. Evaluación genotípica, biológica e inmunológica de la infección en diferentes hospedadores.
    </title>
    <info>
      (Código N018) Proyecto acreditado en el Programa de Incentivos a los Docentes Investigadores del  Ministerio de Cultura y Educación de la Nación, (2013-2016). Informe final aprobado. Proyecto conjunto con la Cátedra de Microbiología y Parasitología de la Facultad de Medicina de la UNCo.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio></anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Estudio de la colonización intestinal de conejos de cría por Escherichia coli productor de toxina Shiga (STEC), primer paso para evaluar su incidencia en la producción,  en la salud del personal dedicado a la actividad y en el medio ambiente.
    </title>
    <info>
      Proyecto Federal de Innovación Productiva. PFIP NQN0042005. Financiado a través del Concurso para la presentación de Proyectos Federales de Innovación Productiva, según Expediente SCTIP 0839/05, Anexo LVIII. Secretaría de Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovación Productiva. Ministerio de Educación, Ciencia y Tecnología de la Nación.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio></anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>
  <cd>
    <title>Incidencia y transmisión de coqueluche en las provincias de Buenos Aires, Neuquén, Santa Fé y Tucumán: implicancias de las características socio sanitarias de la población.
    </title>
    <info>
      Dirigido por la Dra. Daniela Hozbor. Instituto de Biotecnología y Biología Molecular. Facultad Ciencias Exactas. Universidad Nacional de La Plata. Acreedor de una beca Carrillo Oñativia del Ministerio de Salud de la Nación. Año 2010.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Caracterización biológica, inmunológica y molecular del ciclo caprino de Echinococcus granulosus en la Provincia de Neuquén (04/N013).
    </title>
    <info>
      Director: Prof. Dr. Juan Angel Basualdo Farjat Período: 2009-2012. Fuente de financiación: Secretaría de Investigación – UNCo. Informe de avance aprobado, Informe Winsip 2009-2010: Aprobado; Informe final aprobado. Proyecto conjunto con la Cátedra de Microbiología y Parasitología de la Facultad de Medicina de la UNCo.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Caracterización, vigilancia y control de la Hidatidosis en la Provincia de Neuquén: desarrollo y aplicación de nuevas tecnologías para reducir su endemicidad y el impacto social, económico y sanitario en la población provincial.
    </title>
    <info>
      Proyecto Federal de Innovación Productiva, financiado por COFECYT del Ministerio de Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovación Productiva de la Nación. Aprobado en la convocatoria PFIP 2007 según Resolución 395/08. Informe final aprobado. Proyecto conjunto con la Cátedra de Microbiología y Parasitología de la Facultad de Medicina de la UNCo.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio></anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Identificación de la fuente de contagio de pertussis”, que es un componente del SUBPROYECTO 2, Red Nacional de Vigilancia Epidemiológica, del proyecto global: “Producción de una vacuna del Calendario Nacional de Vacunación Argentina. Empleo de estrategias ómicas para el mejoramiento y diseño de nuevas formulaciones.
    </title>
    <info>
      Dirigido por la Dra. Daniela Hozbor. Instituto de Biotecnología y Biología Molecular. Facultad Ciencias Exactas. Universidad Nacional de La Plata. Financiado por el Ministerio de Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovación Productiva. Año 2007.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2007</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

  <cd>
    <title>Coordinación del Área de diagnóstico molecular de la implementación en Neuquén del “Programa Nacional de Vigilancia de Contaminantes Químicos, Biológicos y de Rotulado de Alimentos”
    </title>
    <info>
      Impulsado por ANMAT e instrumentado localmente por la Dirección de Bromatología de la Subsecretaría de Salud de Neuquén.
    </info>

    <tipo>Proyectos de Investigación</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio></anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

  <!--papers-->
  
   <cd>
    <title>Hypervirulent Escherichia coli O157 strains isolated from surface water in cattle breeding areas. 
    </title>
    <info>
   Tanaro JD, Pianciola L, D’Astek BA, Piaggio MC, Mazzeo ML, Zolezzi G, Rivas M. FEMS Microbiology Letters, 2017. En proceso de publicación
    </info>

      <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2017</anio>  <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

    <cd>
    <title>Whole-genome sequencing applied to the molecular epidemiology of Shiga Toxin-producing Escherichia coli O157:H7 in Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
   Claudia Carbonari, Nahuel Fittipaldi, Sarah Teatero, Taryn Athey, Luis Pianciola, Marcelo Masana, Roberto Melano, Marta Rivas, Isabel Chinen. Genome Announcements-American Society for Microbiology, 2016, 4 (6): e01341-16.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>
  
  <cd>
    <title>First study about the development of adult Echinococcus canadensis G6 genotype of goat origin in experimentally infected dogs. 
    </title>
    <info>
 Soriano SV, Debiaggi MF, Pierangeli NB, Pianciola LA, Bergagna HF, Lazzarini LE, Mazzeo ML, Basualdo JA. Veterinary Parasitology, 2016, 228: 6-12.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>  
  <abstract>Echinococcus granulosus sensu lato (E. granulosus sl) must be considered as a species complex, comprising Echinococcusgranulosus sensu stricto (E. granulosus ss, genotypes G1-G3), Echinococcus equinus (G4), Echinococcus ortleppi (G5) and Echinococcus canadensis (G6-G10) although the species status of E. canadensis is still controversial. These genotypes closely match the intermediate hosts associated strains described in earlier times among which E. canadensis G6 corresponds to the camel strain. As there are no studies concerning the development of adult stages of the G6 genotype from non-camel origin, the aims of the present study were: to characterize for the first time the development of E. canadensis G6 in dogs experimentally infected with protoscoleces derived from goats, to describe the resultant adult morphology, to evaluate the growth of their rostellar hooks from larval to adult stages and to determine the prepatent period of the strobilar stage of E. canadensis G6 derived from goats. The development of the strobilar stage of E. canadensis G6 genotype of goat origin was examined by studying the growth (variation of the total worm length) and segmentation in experimentally infected dogs at 14, 25, 35 and 56days post infection. A morphological characterization of 35-day-old worms as well as of larval and adult rostellar hooks was also carried out by conventional optical microscopic observations and/or by scanning electron microscopy. The prepatent period of the strobilar stage was assessed by microscopic examination of faeces from 2 infected dogs. Our results were compared with published data from the camel and other strains. The roles of the host, genotype and species in morphological and developmental features as well as the taxonomic position of E. canadensis G6 were discussed. The prepatent period of E. canadensis G6 genotype of goat origin was determined as at least, 41days. The obtained results contribute to increase the knowledge about the biology and genetics of E. granulosus sl complex and are also of practical usefulness for the design of disease control strategies.</abstract>
  </cd>
  
 <cd>
    <title>Genetic features of human and bovine Escherichia coli O157:H7 strains isolated in Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
 Pianciola L, D’Astek DB, Mazzeo M,  Chinen I, Masana M, Rivas M. International Journal of Medical Microbiology, 2016, 306(2):123-30.
    </info>

  <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2016</anio>
    <abstract>
      Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) are important food-borne pathogens associated with human diseases. In Argentina, O157:H7 is the dominant serotype in hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) cases. Previously, we have described the almost exclusive circulation of human E. coli O157 strains belonging to the hypervirulent clade 8 in Neuquén Province. The aim of the present study was to investigate, by a broad molecular characterization, if this particular distribution of E. coli O157 clades in Neuquén is similar to the situation in other regions of the country and if it may be originated in a similar profile in cattle, its main reservoir. Two-hundred and eighty O157 strains (54 bovine and 226 human) isolated between 2006 and 2008 in different regions of Argentina were studied. All strains harbored rfbO157, fliCH7, eae, and ehxA genes. The predominant genotype was stx2a/stx2c in human (76.1%) and bovine(55.5%) strains. All human isolates tested by Lineage-Specific Polymorphism Assay (LSPA-6), were lineage I/II; among bovine strains, 94.1% belonged to lineage I/II and 5.9% to lineage I. No LSPA-6 lineage II isolates were detected. Single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analysis has revealed the existence of nine clade phylogenetic groups. In our clinical strains collection, 87.6% belonged to the hypervirulent clade 8, and 12.4% were classified as clade 4/5. In bovine isolates, 59.3% strains were clade 8, 33.3% clade 4/5 and 7.4% clade 3. More than 80% of human strains showed the presence of 6 of the 7 virulence determinants described in the TW14359 O157 strain associated with the raw spinach outbreak in the U.S. in 2006. More than 80% of bovine strains showed the presence of 3 of these factors. The q933 allele, which has been related to high toxin production, was present in 98.2% of clinical strains and 75.9% of the bovine isolates. The molecular characterization of human STEC O157 strains allows us to conclude that the particular situation previously described for Neuquén Province, may actually be a characteristic of the whole country. These genetic features are quite similar to those observed in the bovine reservoir and may be derived from it. This data confirms that, unlike the rest of the world, in Argentina most of the STEC O157 strains present in cattle may cause human infections of varying severity and the marked virulence described for these strains may be related to the high incidence of HUS in our country.
    </abstract></cd>
  
 <cd>
    <title>Genotypic characterization of Escherichia coli O157:H7 strains that cause diarrhea and hemolytic uremic syndrome in Neuquén, Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
 Pianciola Luis, Chinen Isabel, Mazzeo Melina, Miliwebsky Elizabeth, González Gladys, Müller Constanza, Carbonari Carolina, Navello Mariano, Zitta Eugenia, Rivas Marta. International Journal of Medical Microbiology, 2014, 304: 499–504.
    </info>

     <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2014</anio>
   <abstract>
     Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) are important food-borne pathogens associated with cases of diarrhea, hemorrhagic colitis and hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS). E. coli O157:H7 is the dominant serotype in Argentina and also in Neuquén Province, in which HUS incidence is above the national average, with a maximum of 28.6 cases per 100,000 children less than 5 years old reported in 1998. The aim of this study was to characterize a collection of 70 STEC O157 strains isolated from patients with diarrhea and HUS treated in the province of Neuquén, Argentina, between 1998 and 2011. All strains harbored eae, ehxA, rfbO157, and fliCH7 genes, and stx2a/stx2c (78.7%) was the predominant genotype. A total of 64 (91.4%) STEC O157 strains belonged to the hypervirulent clade 8 tested using both 4 and 32 SNP typing schemes. The strains showed the highest values reported in the literature for 6 of the 7 virulence determinants described in the TW14359 O157 strain associated with the raw spinach outbreak in the U.S. in 2006. Clade 8 strains were strongly associated with two of them: ECSP_3286, factor encoding an outer membrane protein that facilitates the transport of the heme complex (P=0.001), and in particular extracellular factor ECSP_2870/2872, coding proteins related to adaptation to plant hosts (P=0.000004). The q933 allele, which has been related to high toxin production, was present in 97.1% of the strainsstudied for the anti-terminator Q gene. In summary, this study describes, for the first time in Argentina, the almost exclusive circulation of strains belonging to the hypervirulent clade 8, and also the presence of putative virulence factors in higher frequencies than those reported worldwide. These data may help to understand the causes of the particular epidemiological situation related to HUS in Neuquén Province.
   </abstract>
  </cd>
  
 <cd>
    <title>Laboratory-based prospective surveillance for community outbreaks of Shigella spp. In Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
María Viñas, Ezequiel Tuduri, Alicia Galar, Katherine Yih, Mariana Pichel, John Stelling, Silvina Brengi, Anabella Della Gaspera, Claudia van der Ploeg, Susana Bruno, Ariel Rogé, María Caffer, Martin Killdorff, Marcelo Galas, Group Midas-Argentina. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases, 2013, 7 (12): e2521.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract>BACKGROUND:
To implement effective control measures, timely outbreak detection is essential. Shigella is the most common cause of bacterial diarrhea in Argentina. Highly resistant clones of Shigella have emerged, and outbreaks have been recognized in closed settings and in whole communities. We hereby report our experience with an evolving, integrated, laboratory-based, near real-time surveillance system operating in six contiguous provinces of Argentina during April 2009 to March 2012.
METHODOLOGY:
To detect localized shigellosis outbreaks timely, we used the prospective space-time permutation scan statistic algorithm of SaTScan, embedded in WHONET software. Twenty three laboratories sent updated Shigella data on a weekly basis to the National Reference Laboratory. Cluster detection analysis was performed at several taxonomic levels: for all Shigella spp., for serotypes within species and for antimicrobial resistance phenotypes within species. Shigella isolates associated with statistically significant signals (clusters in time/space with recurrence interval ≥365 days) were subtyped by pulsed field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) using PulseNet protocols.
PRINCIPAL FINDINGS:
In three years of active surveillance, our system detected 32 statistically significant events, 26 of them identified before hospital staff was aware of any unexpected increase in the number of Shigella isolates. Twenty-six signals were investigated by PFGE, which confirmed a close relationship among the isolates for 22 events (84.6%). Seven events were investigated epidemiologically, which revealed links among the patients. Seventeen events were found at the resistance profile level. The system detected events of public health importance: infrequent resistance profiles, long-lasting and/or re-emergent clusters and events important for their duration or size, which were reported to local public health authorities.
CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE:
The WHONET-SaTScan system may serve as a model for surveillance and can be applied to other pathogens, implemented by other networks, and scaled up to national and international levels for early detection and control of outbreaks.
</abstract></cd>

 <cd>
    <title>Outer membrane vesicles derived from Bordetella parapertussis as an acellular vaccine against Bordetella parapertussis and Bordetella pertussis infection. 
    </title>
    <info>
D. Bottero, M.E. Gaillard, A. Errea, G. Moreno, E. Zurita, L. Pianciola, M. Rumbo, D. Hozbor. Vaccine, 2013, 31(45):5262-8.
    </info>
  <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
   <abstract>Bordetella parapertussis, a close related species of B. pertussis, can also cause the disease named pertussis or whooping cough. The number of cases caused by this related pathogen has risen sustained in the last years. The widely used cellular (wP) or acellular(aP) pertussis vaccines have little or no efficacy against B. parapertussis. In an effort to devise an effective acellular vaccine againstB. parapertussis infection, outer membrane vesicles (OMVs) were obtained from B. parapertussis. Proteomic analysis of the resulting OMVs, designated OMVsBpp, evidenced the presence of several surface immunogens including pertactin. The characterized OMVsBpp were used in murine B. parapertussis intranasal challenge model to examine their protective capacity when administered by systemic route. Immunized BALB/c mice were challenged with sublethal doses of B. parapertussis. Significant differences between immunized animals and the negative control group were observed (p smaller than 0.001). OMVsBpp protected against B. parapertussis infection, whereas current commercial aP vaccine showed little protection against such pathogen. More interestingly, protection induced by OMVsBpp against B. pertussis was comparable to our previously designed vaccine consisting in OMVs derived from B. pertussis(OMVsBp). For these experiments we used as a positive control the current commercial aP vaccine in high dose. As expected aP offered protection against B. pertussis in mice. Altogether the results presented here showed that the OMVs from B. parapertussis are an attractive vaccine candidate to protect against whooping cough induced by B. parapertussis but also by B. pertussis.</abstract>
  </cd>

 <cd>
    <title>HTLV-1 cosmopolitan and HTLV-2 sbtype b among pregnant women of non-endemic areas of Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
BeriniC, Delfino C, Torres O, García G, Espejo R, Pianciola L, Juárez M, Arribere G, Nadal M, Eirin M, Biglione M. Sexually Transmited Infections, 2013, 89(4):333-5.
    </info>

     <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2013</anio>
    <abstract>
      OBJECTIVES:
The objective of this study was to estimate the prevalence of human T cell lymphotropic virus (HTLV)-1/2, HIV-1, hepatitis B virus (HBV), Trypanosoma cruzi, Treponema pallidum and Toxoplasma gondii infections and to identify the subtypes/subgroups of HTLV-1/2 among pregnant women (PW) from non-endemic provinces of Argentina.
METHODS:
Methods A total of 2403 samples were screened for HTLV-1/2 and confirmed by western blot and PCR. The long terminal repeat (LTR) of HTLV-1 and HTLV-2 were amplified. Phylogenetic analysis was performed by Neighbour Joining by using molecular evolutionary genetics analysis (MEGA) 4.0.
RESULTS:
Among a total of 2403 PW studied, 6 (0.25%) tested positive for HTLV-1/2 (3 HTLV-1 (0.12%) and 3 HTLV-2 (0.12%)). The total prevalence when distributed by province was 0.3% (3/804) for Buenos Aires (BA), 0.4% (1/241) for BA surroundings, 0.1% (1/707) for Neuquen and 1.0% (1/95) for Ushuaia. In San Juan, no PW were HTLV-1/2 positive. The prevalence was similar when compared with rates among blood donors of the same areas and years. The phylogenetic analysis classified one sequence as HTLV-1aA and one as HTLV-2b. The prevalence of HIV-1, HBV, T cruzi, T pallidum and T gondii was 0.6%, 0.2%, 1.4%, 1.2% and 20.9%, respectively. One case of HTLV-1/HIV-1 and one of HTLV-2/HIV-1 co-infection were detected.
CONCLUSIONS:
HTLV-1/2, which have been associated with different diseases, are circulating among PW of Argentina, even in non-endemic areas. Therefore, testing should be recommended in women who have risk factors for these infections given that the majority of HTLV-1/2 mother to child transmission can be prevented by the avoidance of breast feeding.

    </abstract></cd>

 <cd>
    <title>Medida de ganchos rostelares para diferenciar especies y genotipos de Echinococcus granulosus. 
    </title>
    <info>
Soriano SV, Pierangeli NB, Lazzarini LE, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Kossman A, Basualdo J. Revista Argentina de Zoonosis y Enfermedades Infecciosas Emergentes, 2012, 7: 28.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
   <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

 <cd>
    <title>Desarrollo y validación de una PCR múltiple para el diagnóstico de Bordetella spp. 
    </title>
    <info>
Soriano SV, Pierangeli NB, Lazzarini LE, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Kossman A, Basualdo J. Revista Argentina de Zoonosis y Enfermedades Infecciosas Emergentes, 2012, 7: 28.
    </info>

      <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

 <cd>
    <title>Bordetella holmesii in children suspected of pertussis in Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
Bottero D, Griffith M, Lara C, Flores D, Pianciola L, Gaillard E, Mazzeo M, Zamboni M, Spoletti M, Anchart E, Ruggeri D, Sorhouet C, Flores S, Galas M, Tondella M, Hozbor D. Epidemiology and Infection, 2012, 5: 1-4.
    </info>

      <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2012</anio>
   <abstract>We describe nine patients (eight aged 1 year) clinically diagnosed with pertussis yet laboratory-confirmed with Bordetella holmesiiinfections, a human pathogen normally isolated from blood. Most patients reported cough and cold symptoms. No death was reported. We report B. holmesii isolation in infants with respiratory symptoms in Argentina.</abstract>
  </cd>

 <cd>
    <title>Direct immunofluorescence assay for H1N1 Diagnosis. 
    </title>
    <info>
Carta al Comité Editor. Pianciola L, González G, Mazzeo M, Navello M, Quidel N, Bulgheroni MF. Revista Panamericana de Salud Pública-Pan American Journal of Public Health, 2011, 29(3): 211-2.
    </info>

     <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2011</anio>
    <abstract></abstract></cd>

<cd>
    <title>Optimización del procesamiento y la conservación de muestras clínicas destinadas al diagnóstico molecular de coqueluche. 
    </title>
    <info>
L. Pianciola, M. Mazzeo, D. Flores, D. Hozbor. Revista Argentina de Microbiología, 2010, 42: 108-113.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
  <abstract>Pertussis or whooping cough is an acute, highly contagious respiratory infection, which is particularly severe in infants under one year old. In classic disease, clinical diagnosis may present no difficulties. In other cases, it requires laboratory confirmation. Generally used methods are: culture, serology and PCR. For the latter, the sample of choice is a nasopharyngeal aspirate, and the simplest method for processing these samples uses proteinase K. Although results are generally satisfactory, difficulties often arise regarding the mucosal nature of the specimens. Moreover, uncertainties exist regarding the optimal conditions for sample storage. This study evaluated various technologies for processing and storing samples. Results enabled us to select a method for optimizing sample processing, with performance comparable to commercial methods and far lower costs. The experiments designed to assess the conservation of samples enabled us to obtain valuable information to guide the referral of samples from patient care centres to laboratories where such samples are processed by molecular methods.</abstract>
  </cd>

<cd>
    <title>Automated use of WHONET and SaTScan to detect outbreaks of Shigella spp using antimicrobial resistance phenotypes. 
    </title>
    <info>
J. Stelling, W. K. Yih, M. Galas, M. Kulldorff, M. Pichel, R. Terragno, E. Tuduri, S. Espetxe, N. Binsztein, T. F. O’Brien, R. Platt and Collaborative Group Whonet-Argentina. Epidemiology and Infection, 2010, 138: 873-883.
    </info>

     <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract>Antimicrobial resistance is a priority emerging public health threat, and the ability to detect promptly outbreaks caused by resistant pathogens is critical for resistance containment and disease control efforts. We describe and evaluate the use of an electronic laboratory data system (WHONET) and a space-time permutation scan statistic for semi-automated disease outbreak detection. In collaboration with WHONET-Argentina, the national network for surveillance of antimicrobial resistance, we applied the system to the detection of local and regional outbreaks of Shigella spp. We searched for clusters on the basis of genus, species, and resistancephenotype and identified 19 statistical 'events' in a 12-month period. Of the six known outbreaks reported to the Ministry of Health, four had good or suggestive agreement with SaTScan-detected events. The most discriminating analyses were those involving resistance phenotypes. Electronic laboratory-based disease surveillance incorporating statistical cluster detection methods can enhance infectious disease outbreak detection and response.</abstract></cd>

<cd>
    <title>Desempeño de la prueba de inmunofluorescencia directa en el diagnóstico del virus Influenza A(H1N1). 
    </title>
    <info>
Pianciola L, González G, Mazzeo M, Navello M, Quidel N, Bulgheroni MF. Revista  Panamericana de Salud Pública-Pan American Journal of Public Health, 2010, 27(6):452–4.
    </info>

     <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
 <abstract></abstract>
  </cd>

<cd>
    <title>Molecular characterization of Echinococcus isolates indicates goats as reservoir for Echinococcus Canadensis G6 genotype in Neuquén, Patagonia Argentina. 
    </title>
    <info>
Soriano SV, Pierangeli NB, Pianciola L, Mazzeo M, Lazzarini LE, Saiz MS, Kossman AV, Bergagna HFJ, Chartier K, Basualdo JA. Parasitology International, 2010, 59(4): 626-8.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2010</anio>
    <abstract>Human cystic echinococcosis is a highly endemic zoonotic disease in the province of Neuquén, Patagonia Argentina, although a hydatid control programme has been carried out since 1970. Human infection due to Echinococcus canadensis (G6 genotype) is frequent in Neuquén. However, the reservoir for this species remains undetermined in a region where camels are absent. We investigated the fertility, viability and molecular epidemiology of hydatid cysts obtained from local goats, pigs and sheep in order to identify the possible reservoirs of E. canadensis (G6). We also analyzed isolates from infected dogs. A total of 67 isolates were identified by the DNA sequencing of the mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 gene. Cysts from sheep (n=16), goats (n=23) and pigs (n=18) and adult worms from 10 infected dogs were analyzed. The fertility of the hydatid cysts was 78.6%; 90.4% and 94.4% for sheep, goats and pigs, respectively. We detected E. canadensis (G6) in 21 of 23 goat samples and in 1 dog isolate, E. canadensis(G7) in all the pig isolates, E. granulosus sensu stricto (G3) in 1 sheep and the G1 genotype in 15 sheep, 2 goats and 9 dog samples. The G1 haplotypes included the common sheep strain sequence and 2 microvariants of this sequence. E. granulosus sensu stricto (G3) is described for the first time in South America. We conclude that goats act as reservoir for E. canadensis (G6) in Neuquén, and that control strategies may have to be adapted to local molecular epidemiology to improve the control of parasite transmission.</abstract></cd>

<cd>
    <title>Pertussis epidemiology in Argentina: trends over 2004-2007.
    </title>
    <info>
 D. Hozbor, F. Mooi, D. Flores, G. Weltman, D. Bottero, S. Fossati, C. Lara, M. E. Gaillard, L. Pianciola, E. Zurita, A. Fioriti, D. Archuby, M. Galas, N. Binsztein, M. Regueira, C. Castuma, M. Fingermann, A. Graieb. Journal of Infection, 2009, 56: 225-31.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2009</anio>
 <abstract>
   OBJECTIVES:
Pertussis continues causing significant morbidity and mortality worldwide. Although its epidemiology has been studied in many developed countries, the current pertussis situation in South America is scarcely known. This review summarizes the most important recent data concerning pertussis in a country of South America, Argentina.
METHODS:
CDC criteria were used for pertussis diagnosis. Proportion of pertussis cases by age, immunization status, and immunization coverage rate evaluated at the Argentinean National Pertussis Reference Centers was reported. Bordetella pertussisisolates were characterized and compared with vaccine strains.
RESULTS:
From 2002 to nowadays, a steady increase of pertussis cases was observed. Most of these cases correspond to patients younger than six months old that received less than three doses of vaccine. However, cases in adolescent and adults have also been detected. For this situation, which is not peculiar to Argentina, several explanations have been proposed. Among them, the inability of current vaccines to induce long-lasting immunity is the most widely accepted as a cause of pertussis resurgence. Furthermore, antigenic divergence between local clinical isolates and vaccine strains may have aggravated the effect of waning immunity.
CONCLUSIONS:
Pertussis is an important problem for public health in Argentina. Divergence between vaccine strains and local isolates could contribute to the described pertussis epidemiology.

 </abstract>
  </cd>

<cd>
    <title>Genetic characterization of human hydatid cysts shows coinfection by Echinococcus canadensis G7 and Echinococcus granulosus sensu stricto G1 in Argentina.
    </title>
    <info>
 María Florencia Debiaggi; Silvia Viviana Soriano; Nora Beatriz Pierangeli; Lorena Evelina Lazzarini; Luis Alfredo Pianciola; Melina Leonor Mazzeo; Sergio Moguillansky; Juan Angel Basualdo Farjat. PARASITOLOGY RESEARCH, 2017. En Prensa.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2017</anio>
    <abstract>
      Human cystic echinococcosis caused by the larval stage of Echinococcus granulosus sensu lato (s.l.) is a highly endemic disease in the province of Neuquén, Patagonia, Argentina. Human infections with E. granulosus sensu stricto (s.s.) G1 and Echinococcus canadensis G6 were reported in Neuquén in previous studies, whereas four genotypes were identified in livestock: G1, G3, G6, and G7. The aim of this study was to identify the genotypes of E. granulosus s.l. isolates from humans of Neuquén province, Patagonia, Argentina, through the 2005–2014 period. Twenty six hydatid cysts were obtained from 21 patients. The most frequent locations were the liver and lungs. Single cysts were observed in 81.0% of patients, and combined infection of liver and lungs was detected in 9.5% of cases. Partial sequencing of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 (cox1) and NADH dehydrogenase subunit 1 (nad1) genes identified the presence of E. granulosus s.s. G1 (n = 11; 42.3%) including three different partial sequences; E. canadensis G6 (n = 14; 53.8%) and E. canadensis G7 (n = 1; 3.9%). Coinfection with G1 and G7 genotypes was detected in one patient who harbored three liver cysts. Most of the liver cysts corresponded to G1 and G6 genotypes. This study presents the first report in the Americas of a human infection with E. canadensis G7 and the second worldwide report of a coinfection with two different species and genotypes of E. granulosus s.l in humans. The molecular diversity of this parasite should be considered to redesign or improve the control program strategies in endemic regions.
    </abstract></cd>

  
  <cd>
    <title>Virulence profile of Escherichia coli O157 strains isolated from surface water in cattle breeding areas.
    </title>
    <info>
 Tanaro JD; Pianciola LA; D'Astek BA, Piaggio MC, Mazzeo ML, Zolezzi G, Rivas M., 2018. En proceso de publicación.
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2018</anio>
    <abstract>
     Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) O157:H7 is a worldwide concern. Cattle are their main reservoir and may contaminate watercourses through manure. We characterized a collection of 38 STEC O157:H7 strains isolated from surface water in feedlots areas (puddles inside pens formed after the rainfall or by spill around drinking troughs, and small water courses and lagoons, formed by runoff). Nineteen (50.0%) strains harbored stx2a /stx2c genes, 18 (47.4%) stx2c and one stx1a /stx2c . All strains harbored eae, ehxA, rfbO157 , and fliCH7 genes, and the putative virulence determinants ECSP_0242, ECSP_2687 and ECSP_3620. All isolates tested as Lineage I/II by lineage-specific polymorphism assay-6. Nineteen (50%) belonged to the high virulent clade 8. The q21 allele was found in all strains and q933 /q21 alleles in 17 (44.7%). By XbaI-pulsed-field gel electrophoresis, 29 strains were grouped into 7 clusters. Four clusters grouped isolates from distant places separated by 150-250 Km. This may be related to vectors, like birds, involved in their spread. Otherwise, three clusters contained isolates recovered at same places with intervals of 1 to 9 months. This could be explained by the high environmental persistence of STEC O157:H7. These strains recovered from surface water showed similar genotypes to those found in the bovine reservoir and in human diseases, and could be linked to the high incidence of hemolytic uremic syndrome in Argentina. 
    </abstract></cd>
  
   <cd>
    <title>Genotypic Features of Clinical and Bovine Escherichia coli O157 Strains Isolated in Countries with Different Associated-Disease Incidences</title>
    <info>
 Luis Pianciola,  Marta Rivas. 27 de abril de 2018
    </info>

    <tipo>Publicaciones en Revistas Científicas</tipo>
    <lugar></lugar>
    <anio>2018</anio>
    <abstract>
    There is great geographical variation in the frequency of Escherichia coli O157 infections that
correlates with important differences in the bovine reservoir of each country. Our group carried out a
broad molecular characterization of human and bovine E. coli O157 strains circulating in Argentina
using different methodologies. Our data allows us to conclude that in Argentina, a high homogeneity
is observed in both cattle and human strains, with almost exclusive circulation of strains belonging to
the hypervirulent clade 8 described by Manning. The aim of this review was to compare the genetic
background of E. coli O157 strains isolated in countries that have conducted similar studies, to try to
correlate specific O157 genotypes with the incidence and severity of E. coli O157 associated diseases.
The characteristics of the strains that cause disease in humans reflect the predominant genotypes in
cattle in each of the countries analyzed. The main features clearly linked to high incidence or severity
of E. coli O157 infections are lineage-specific polymorphism assay-6 lineage I/II, clade 8 strains and
probably, clade 6 strains, the stx2a/stx2c genotype, the presence of q933 and q21 simultaneously,
and putative virulence factor EC_3286. In countries with an absence of these features in O157 strains,
the overall incidence of O157 disease is low. Argentina, where these characteristics are detected in
most strains, shows the highest incidence of hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) worldwide. 
    </abstract></cd>
  <!--Capítulos de Libros-->

<cd>
    <title>
      MANUAL DE MICROBIOLOGÍA CLÍNICA DE LA ASOCIACION ARGENTINA DE MICROBIOLOGÍA VOLUMEN I. Bacterias de Importancia Clínica. Capítulo II.c.4.3 BORDETELLA. 
   
    </title>
    <info>
          Editores: Dres. Horacio Lopardo, Silvia C. Predari, Carlos Vay
 
    </info>

    <tipo>Capítulos de Libros</tipo>
    <lugar>
   Autores: Daniela Hozbor, Luis Pianciola, Claudia Lara, Daniela Bottero.
    </lugar>
    <anio></anio>
    <abstract>
    
    </abstract></cd>
</catalog>